[bagpipes]
♪ Push it to the limit
When I get into a rhythm ♪
♪ I'm seeing visions
Working hard and never wishin' ♪
♪ Looking for that vision
Muscle and ambition ♪
♪ The only one to meet
The real competition ♪
[girl] Come on! [sighs]
[girl] Come on! Come on!
[girl] These boys did this last year!
We can't lose!
[boy] Watch out!
Geocache champions coming through!
[girl 2] I see them!
[boy] Give up! You know we're gonna win!
-[girl] Back off, buttfaces!
-Yeah!
[girl] Yoli, hurry! They're catching up!
[boy] We got the next clue!
-[girl] Yoli, dead ahead, it's a shortcut!
-[Yoli] You got it, Pili!
[Pili] Dang it, they all followed!
Come on, Yoli, hurry!
[boy] Loser!
[Pili] Brace yourself!
♪ Only time I'm laying low
Is when I wanna race ♪
-[car horns beeping]
-[Pili] Yes!
[boy] Look out!
[boy] Sorry!
-[Pili] Yoli, hard left!
-I got it.
[Pili] Sorry! Out of the way!
-[screaming]
-[Pili] Hope those are clean!
[Pili] Sorry, folks, it's a competition!
[both panting]
♪ If you're good then you're good
I'm good at this ♪
Okay.
-[boy] Coming through!
-[boy 2] Heads up!
-Balls!
-[boy] Here we go.
-[girls huff]
What does it say next?
"Go straight to the bottom
and you'll find the key to the cache,
numbers inclined."
Straight to the bottom?
Yoli, remember that video I sent you?
About the tunnels underneath the pools?
-The pool's not the bottom!
-Exactly!
-Over there! Come on.
-[boy 2] Where are they going?
[Pili] Come on, straight ahead!
[android voice] Attention, geocachers.
There are five minutes remaining.
[Yoli] Come on!
-Pili, they're all different.
-So are the combinations!
[boy] Are you seeing this?
[boy 2] Come on, let's go.
[boy] What is all this stuff?
[Pili] "Go straight to the bottom
and you'll find
the key to the cache, numbers inclined."
Numbers inclined!
[creaking]
Yoli, it's--
[in Spanish]
The box with a five-number lock!
Okay!
[in Spanish] I got it!
Seven…
two… one…
five… six!
Six!
[crowd cheering]
[in English] It was tough,
but you all did great,
so please give it up for yourselves!
You have won a trip
to our Geocache Camp
in the Catskills!
Woo!
Hit it, DJ!
It's gonna be the best summer ever!
NETFLIX PRESENTS
[Leilani] Clopidogrel.
It's generic for Plavix for my father.
He had a heart attack a week ago.
Okay. Perfect, thank you.
O'AHU, HAWAI'I
[NOT THE CATSKILLS]
-Hey!
-I just need it for two minutes.
Get a job and buy your own.
It's important! Yoli said she'd tell me
all about the Geocamp I'm missing.
Mom!
Pili, relax. You can check your email
when you get in the house.
What if Papa doesn't have internet?
Dad, hello!
[Leilani] Oh, jeez.
-Ew, ants!
-It's smells like…
Old people and disappointment.
What is this?
Final notice?
Dad!
What's that?
Oh, the second sign we're in hell.
The first being no Wi-Fi.
Mom! How am I gonna know
what I'm missing at camp now?
Oh, Dad.
Hey!
What are you doing? Jeez!
-Mom!
-Ioane, please don't kill your sister.
Ow!
You just nearly tore off my nip!
That's what you get
for being a salty bunghole!
That's enough.
[in Hawaiian] Make things right.
-Me? She ripped my nip off!
-Apologize to him? Of all people!
[in Hawaiian] Make things right!
Ioane, you first.
I'm sorry that you're so annoying.
I'm sorry your boy udders are so massive.
Forgive me for breaking
your GeoCrap Stick Mirror on purpose.
Forgive me rubbing my butt
on your pillow and giving you pink eye.
Thank you for giving me a reason to burn--
Ioane!
Dad!
-I hate you.
[Ioane huffs]
[mocking voice]
Mom, I thought you said
Papa was gonna have Wi-Fi.
Chill, Pils. It's a stupid camp
for fake treasure hunting.
You know what's stupid? Your face.
Stupid is buying two pairs of shoes
and wearing one of each.
-You know what's stupid? Your whole--
-Hey!
[in Hawaiian Pidgin] What you guys doing?
You guys arguing isn't doing anything.
I'll give you spankings for that.
What did he say?
Dad, what are you doing up there?
You're supposed to be in bed resting.
I'm Hawaiian. I take care of the land.
For ten years,
I have nobody telling me what for do.
You come here, you tell me what for do.
Dr. Campos said he wants you on bed rest!
I don't care what Dr. Campos says.
You didn't have to come over here!
Of course we're gonna come!
You guys look more taller in the picture.
More skinny, too.
-Go ahead, brah. Chance 'em.
-Seems a little unsanitary.
Just eat it.
Thanks?
Mahalo.
Go ahead, say "mahalo."
You couldn't take a moment
to teach these kids a little Hawaii?
Of course not. We live in New York.
Just a little Hawaii,
that's all I was asking you.
-It's raining. Let's go.
-[Kimo] What about you, boy?
-You dance hula?
-[Leilani] Of course he doesn't.
You could talk Hawaiian anyplace.
Chance 'em.
[Leilani] Nobody in New York
understands it.
Monks?
What is that?
Hawaiian?
[Speaking Spanish] Así luego,
en la oscuridad de la noche
Robinson y Brown--
[in English] Kill us and keep the gold?
[indistinct conversation]
Err...
Ugh!
[rattling]
Cheese on rice!
-That was some John Wick fancy business.
-Sssh.
Are you a thief?
Please, no one's stealing
anything in there.
-What is that?
-None ya business.
Who are you?
That's fair. I'm Casper. Aloha.
Pili.
So, Kimo's your grandpa, right?
Genetically.
-What's up with your cat?
-Oh, that's Mortimer.
He's obese so I have to walk him.
Or he'll end up with diabetes.
-But you're dragging him around.
-I'm trying to motivate him.
Where you come from, girl?
She came over to meet Mortimer.
Yeah.
[cat yowls]
-That… means he likes you!
-[both nervously giggling]
Are we going to do the thing or what?
-Yeah.
-All right.
Red-crested cardinal,
you look like you knew
how to have a great time.
[in Hawaiian] Until we meet again.
[in English] Rest in peace.
Wait, that wasn't your bird?
No. They're not my pets.
I still think it's sad they died.
I guess it would suck if no one cared.
We honor the dead by talking stories…
and keeping their wailua alive,
their spirit,
with… aloha.
Woah.
Breathtaking.
Mom, where'd you say
that Hawaiian dictionary was?
Did you look in my desk?
HAWAIIAN-ENGLISH DICTIONARY
[Leilani] Sugarcane, did you hear me?
[kiss]
Did you find the--
Never seen this pic of Dad before.
Kua.
I forgot I had this.
Er, Pili…
I know you're upset about
not being able to go to your camp,
so…
what if you and I go geocaching tomorrow?
Yeah! I haven't looked up
the caches around here yet.
-I bet they have some really cool ones.
-Great! Tomorrow then.
[speaking Spanish]
"Marchadores nocturnos"?
Lapu? Night Marchers?
Hey, give it back! What are you--
-It's not yours!
-A drawing of a nightmarcher?
You know what that is?
Yeah, ghosts of Hawaiian warriors.
Bobby Shytles told me about it
after his trip to Maui.
What's Bobby the Turd know about Hawaii?
What doesn't he know about Hawaii?
He said they march at night,
protecting the island.
You'll know they're coming
when you hear their drums.
[rhythmic knocking]
Ta-ta-ta, ta-ta-ta, ta-ta
Then you'll see their torches…
like a string of lights.
If you hear their shell horn thing,
forget it.
They're close.
-And if they find you…
-What?
You better kiss the ground
and keep your head down,
'cause if not…
Remember that scene
from Raiders of the Lost Ark
where the Nazis' faces melt off?
That.
Well, sleep tight.
[whimpers]
[birds chirping in distance]
That's disgusting.
No, this food is. No pepper,
no salt, no flavor.
Who's this for? We ain't white.
-Egg whites are good for your heart--
-Five years, Dad.
[Leilani] Five years!
How could you not have paid
your property taxes in five years?
Why didn't you tell me
you were in trouble?
[Kimo] I take care of myself!
[Leilani] Really?
'Cause you're about to lose your house!
Dad, I know you don't want to hear this,
but maybe you would be better off
in New York. You could get around easier.
This is my kuleana.
This is our ohana's land!
Not like you,
I'm gonna die before I leave.
-E, get ready. We're leaving in ten.
-What? Where are you going?
We're gonna go pick up Papa's meds
and a new router.
E said something about needing
a stronger one or something.
I just need to take care of a few things.
But I thought
we were gonna go geocaching today.
I packed for two.
Oh, Sugarcane. I'm so sorry,
not today. Okay?
Maybe tomorrow.
[knocks at door]
Aloha, I'm Casper.
Would Pilialoha be around?
["Blush", CounterCulture playing]
♪ When I first saw you ♪
♪ I fell in love ♪
♪ And I know that you fell for me too ♪
♪ No matter what they say ♪
♪ You gave it away ♪
♪ The moment I said hello to you ♪
♪ I saw you blush ♪
♪ I'm your crush ♪
♪ Baby, woooo! ♪
♪ Blush ♪
[song fades]
Let me guess.
You're not Pili, but her brother?
E.
Like the letter?
It's short for equal pay. Am I right?
Just kidding. It's short for Ioane.
-And you are?
-Hana.
Hana.
Hana, what is that, Japanese?
It's also Hawaiian.
Like Ioane.
-That's me.
-Yeah.
About Pili.
-Is she here?
-Gingerbread, move along. We're talking.
-Don't do that.
-Do what?
Act like a tool.
Answer his question. Is your sister here?
Erm. Yeah. She's out back, dude.
I finish work at 3:00.
Call me if you need a ride home.
-Mahalo for the ride.
-Yeah, of course.
-It's so long!
-[Hana laughs]
Nice to meet you, Hudson!
So, Hana, we should-- Oh, these are nice.
"As the sun set and the rain fell,
we cut our own path."
O'AHU, HAWAI'I 1823
"Robinson pushed us forward
through untouched land
filled with exotic sights, strange sounds,
and Brown marked our way."
"And I,
the ship's quartermaster,
recorded it."
[blowing]
[Casper] Hey, Pili!
Pili.
Pili?
[Casper] Woo! [panting]
Okay.
Casper! You can't sneak up
on a New Yorker!
-People die doing that.
-Ow!
I wasn't trying to.
And aren't you Hawaiian?
Yeah, but we moved to New York
when I was one.
Anyways, don't expect an apology.
I'm too progressive.
I'm sorry you had to hit me?
You grew up here.
How much Hawaiian do you know?
Not much.
My friend Hana knows more.
-Why?
-I'm trying to translate these,
but I gotta do it word by word
and it's taking forever.
Most of this is in Spanish.
-You know Spanish?
-Yeah.
I got tired of explaining to people
I wasn't Puerto Rican, so I learned it.
-Whose journal is this?
-Some dude named Monks.
-A sailor on the--
-Peruvian.
The Peruvian's treasure's legendary.
Treasure? Like, real treasure?
People are looking for it.
I can't believe this is Monks!
What's it say?
Okay. So…
As you know, Spanish colonizers hired
a bunch of privateers to hide their gold,
but then Robinson and Brown
discovered a secret.
[clears throat] "Monks!"
Robinson and Brown told Monks:
"Yo, fam, our captain's gonna kill us
and keep all that sweet gold for himself!"
And then Monks was like: "That sucks!"
"It's real wack."
"Dawg, you wanna mutinize?"
And Monks was like:
"Yeah, that sounds lit."
-"He-he-he!"
-"Ha-ha-ha!"
So they did a mutiny.
Brown could kill with a piece of bread.
And as the Peruvian burnt down,
Robinson, Brown, Monks,
and a handful of trusted privateers
hauled the treasure ashore.
And that's when they decided:
"Yo, let's hide the treasure here."
"Yeah, so we can get a new ship
and peace out."
And that's as far as I got.
-Do you care about spoilers?
-No.
After they hid the treasure,
Monks stayed behind to guard it
while Robinson and Brown
sailed back to England,
but their ship never made it.
Oh, snap!
A storm hit their ship
and everyone on it was lost at sea.
And Monks, he was almost beaten to death.
He was crawling around
in the hot sand. Poor guy.
[Pili] He was almost beaten to death
by who?
It's a mystery. An old Hawaiian couple
found him just in the nick of time.
Monks must have given his journal to them
as a thanks for saving his life.
If Robinson, Brown, and Monks
didn't get to the treasure, where is it?
No one knows.
One theory is Monks told
the couple where it was,
but no one's ever cashed in
a fortune's worth of Spanish gold.
I really gotta finish reading this.
[Kimo grunts]
[Kimo] Hey!
So…
you stole from me.
I am your papa. I'm your grandfather.
[Pili growls]
[Kimo sighs]
Wait!
I left something in the book.
-Hey, where'd you get that?
-Mom's room.
She didn't say I couldn't have it.
I didn't steal it.
[mimicking] "I didn't steal it."
Hand it over, mongoose.
-I'm not a mongoose.
-Hand it over.
Wow!
Your mother is so happy here, look.
This was just before your father
went to join the Army.
You know what?
You have your father's smile.
-Really?
-Really.
This was my papa's,
who got it from his papa,
who got it from Monks.
So, my great-great-great-great--
Our family saved Monks' life?
And my papa's papa…
got this from Monks.
-Woo. Is it real?
-Of course it's real, look again.
Then where's the rest of it?
-Why aren't you living in a mansion?
-A mansion?
Look around, we Hawaiian. We kanaka.
-We're so lucky for live in Hawaii.
-So, you're saying you never found it.
[Kimo laughs]
Oh, look at this.
Mokoli'i. So beautiful, yeah?
What you think?
-Keoki! How's it?
-Kimo!
-Aloha, Kimo!
-Aloha, brother.
Brah. Made you a little pu'olo.
Get that lomi salmon, pipikaula,
and fresh poi.
I love this. Mahalo, Kimo.
Remember the last time we was here?
We went fishing over there.
I remember, it was just over there!
We caught the menpachi.
I still got him in my freezer.
I love them. I ate them all.
We gotta do it again. If I get to it,
great. If not, no big deal.
Brah, I know you can! Guaranteed, brah!
What are you guys saying?
Little Pili.
Pili?
Wow! The last time I saw you,
you were a little baby.
Here, I make some musubi for you.
And please, tell your mom aloha for me.
It's been a long time since I've seen her.
-Yeah.
-Let's go to the boat.
All right.
Watch out for the reef.
Catch you folks on by.
'Kay, brah.
Slick shoes.
You know you're gonna get them wet?
Hey, come on. We gotta go.
Come on. Let's go.
You guys know I can't swim, right?
[Kimo] Grab the steering wheel.
What kind of Hawaiian
are you going to be if you no can swim?
We don't have to swim across rivers
in New York. We got trains for that.
Papa gonna teach you,
if you don't drown first.
Quick, put this on. Quick. Put 'em on.
Attagirl!
Here we go, brah!
-Woohoo!
[Kimo] All right!
[Pili] Woo!
[cheers in Hawaiian]
[conch echoing]
As I was saying,
New York has real winters, though.
It isn't really Christmas
until the air is so cold,
your lungs burn when you breathe.
[Kimo] Wait.
No Mele Kalikimaka until your lungs hurt?
[Pili] Christmas in New York is the best.
Open the bag. Let's see what we got.
Oh, spam musubi made by Keoki.
Go ahead.
All right.
-[Pili] Mmm.
-[Kimo] Mmm?
[Pili] Mmm!
[Kimo] Mmm.
[Pili] You know,
New York's not always cold.
You've never been.
Maybe you should come visit.
Cannot be as beautiful as this island,
the people.
We live aloha.
Aloha is how we treat ourselves,
how we help others,
how we know…
where we supposed to be in this life.
Kuleana. Our responsibility.
How we take care of the island.
And aloha's a big part of you.
You know why?
Because you…
Hawaiian… and you get koko,
Hawaiian blood.
Hey, look over there. What do you see?
Mountains?
[Pili] This is where they first landed!
Ae.
[Kimo] Where are you going?
Look! It's Robinson and Brown's mark.
Oh, you speak Spanish, yeah?
I had to translate it one word at a time
and it took me forever.
So these Post-it notes in Hawaiian,
these are you?
Ae.
"We placed the jewel inside the crown
and marked it with gold."
[Pili gasps]
Go ahead. Look through.
Take a look over there.
Is that where Monks went?
Is that where we have to go next
to find the treasure?
There is no treasure.
The book is the treasure.
Here.
Hey, where you going?
I want to make sure the coin shows
the same spot from higher up.
-Papa don't like you going up there.
-Why, is it dangerous?
Of course it's dangerous. Tourists ruined
the road up there. It's all eroded.
I'm small. It'll be fine.
Pilialoha, get down here right now!
Don't worry, I'll be right back!
[Kimo grunts]
Papa!
[Ioane] Service. Service.
Yes!
Er. Ioane.
-E. Can I talk to you for a second?
-Yeah.
Also, where are we going?
I don't see a Best Buy anywhere.
Hold on. Let me pull over.
Ioane, I have to talk to you
about something.
So…
Papa is having a hard time
paying his bills, and…
he might lose his house.
So, property values in Greenpoint
have gone up--
You want to sell our apartment
to pay his bills.
Please just try to understand.
That land has been in our family
for generations.
-It's our home.
-We grew up in New York. It's our home.
Papa built that house
with his own two hands.
He had a heart attack
and we were not there!
You're hardly there for us
and we live with you!
Do you know how hard it is to raise
two kids alone in New York?
Yes, Mom.
Every time I hit the bodega,
or I make dinner,
or I do laundry because you can't.
That's not fair.
What's not fair is losing my whole life
because you feel guilty about
leaving Hawaii when Dad died.
How dare you!
[mobile ringtone]
Hello?
-Mom, something happened to Papa!
-Pili, slow down. I can't understand--
Hurry! Something happened to Papa!
We gotta go.
-Are you gonna have him stay overnight?
-Yeah.
-With his medical history…
-Pils.
Hey.
It's just a broken rib. He'll live.
-You should be more worried about us.
-Huh?
If Mom can't pay off Papa's bills,
he's not moving to Brooklyn--
He said he'd rather die.
Which is why Mom told me
she wants to sell our apartment
and move us here.
I know. Jessica Riley just told me
she was gonna make out with me,
and I'm not spending my senior year
stuck on this stupid island.
[door opens]
[footsteps]
Papa? Is he okay? What did they say?
No, Pilialoha, he is not okay.
I can't believe you asked him
to take you to Mokolli'i!
-But I didn't--
-I don't want to hear it.
They're keeping him overnight,
so I'm gonna stay too.
You two go home.
-It wasn't even my--
-I said go home.
-[Pili sighs]
-[door closes]
Papa's hurt and it's my fault.
Oh, no. Please don't cry.
Don't tell me not to cry
when I'm trying not to. It doesn't help.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
[Pili sniffs]
Ew!
Kimo's tough.
One time I saw him invite
two Mormon missionaries in for coffee.
He'll be okay.
It's not just that he's hurt.
He can't pay his bills.
He might lose his house.
I have to find a way to fix it.
How? There isn't any gold
at the end of our double rainbows.
It'd be cool if there were though.
Pils, geocaching really just snapped
your grasp on reality, hasn't it?
Papa said Monks gave it to our family.
It's real gold, E!
I bit it, you can see my teeth marks.
Now I know you're both crazy.
Why is your hair
the same color as your nips?
-Don't objectify him!
-What?
No, I didn't mean--
That's not even how you use the word.
If Mom can't pay Papa's bills,
we gotta leave Brooklyn.
This is how we can get the money.
Real money, Pils.
We need legit bank, not some crusty gelt.
Fine. Whatever.
TRUCK
You can't just walk into Kualoa.
It's trespassing.
Fine. I'll sneak in.
-You'll get caught.
-Then I'll pretend I'm lost.
Trust me,
adults are dumb and I'm adorable.
But, Pili, Kualoa, it's--
I gotta do this, Casper, for Papa.
[Casper exhales]
Okay. We'll go at dawn.
We?
For Mr. Kimo.
[Pili grunts]
D is for Drive, right?
What? You said you knew how to drive.
Chill. I know what I'm doing.
[radio plays]
Hold your tater tots.
[engine rattling]
[revs]
[Casper shouts]
[song in Hawaiian playing]
[Pili] Wow, it sure is quiet here.
You know folks in New York honk 24/7?
[Casper] This is Hawaii. Honking is rude.
Pili, please pull over. I don't feel good.
I think I'm gonna lose it.
[screeches]
[retches]
I wasn't that bad.
Come on, Barfy. Let's go!
[sighs]
NOTICE - EMPLOYEES ONLY
VISITORS PLEASE USE FRONT ENTRANCE
-Hold Keanu.
-Okay.
-It's heavy!
-Oh! Jeez, what do you got in here, dude?
KUALOA RANCH
So you're telling me that people
come here just to see a few hills?
Kualoa Valley is sacred Hawaiian land,
but also they shoot a lot of movies
like Jurassic Park here.
Really? That's so--
What?
Wooo!
This is dope, yo!
Mortimer would have enjoyed this.
[mobile ringtone]
Sorry, Mom. Not the time.
Come on. Let's go.
[telephone ringing]
[ringing]
[Ioane] Huh?
-Why aren't you answering your cell phone?
-I don't know.
It's too early.
I'm calling to check up on you guys.
-How's Pili?
-Still annoying.
-Can I talk to her?
-Let me see if she's up.
Old people phones.
Hello? E? You still there?
Oh, no, is Pili mad at me?
Er. Yeah. No, I mean,
she's in the bathroom making a poop.
Oh, she'll be a while then.
You know it!
That girl needs more fiber in her diet.
-Can you make sure she has a banana?
-How's Papa?
He slept through the night,
but we're waiting on more tests.
Uh-huh. Well, that sucks.
Yeah. Well, there's a shower here, so…
if you guys could just bring me
a change of clothes, I'd appreciate it.
Er. Yeah. I told Pili I was gonna take her
geocaching this morning to cheer her up,
so maybe after that.
Oh, E, that's so sweet of you. Thank you!
It's all good, Mom!
Okay, have fun geocaching.
And try not to kill each other.
-Call me before--
-Okay, cool. Bye.
Pili!
Who comes all the way to Hawaii
just to see where they film Lost?
People really liked Lost.
I thought it was convoluted
and poorly plotted.
I guess after six years
of accumulated emotional investment,
people don't want to admit
they spent time
on something that failed to deliver
a satisfying ending.
The cinematography work was great though.
Dude, got enough sunscreen?
People are so weird.
This place is pretty enough
to visit on its own.
[horse snorting]
Oh, balls.
-Is "balls" a New York thing?
-Come on!
Come on, hurry up!
[heavy galloping]
Hey, you! Behind the sign!
-Bye! Every man for himself!
-Wait! Pili!
-Pili!
-I come in peace.
-I had no idea--
-Ryan! It's me, Casper.
Brah. I thought you were
some trespassing haole tourists.
-I was showing my friend Pili around.
-On foot?
Yeah.
[revving]
Why didn't you tell me
you know people who work here?
You were so excited about sneaking in.
I didn't wanna ruin your fun.
-You're such a weirdo!
-Mahalo!
Onward to treasure!
Yo, what's up? It's E.
Leave me a message.
I know you're at Kualoa, Pili,
and when I find you, I'll kill you,
then I'll wake you back up--
KUALOA
WELCOME TO HAWAII! THE OKUMURAS
Hana Okumura.
OAHU OKUMURA PHONE NUMBER
A hundred thirty-three Okumuras.
How big is this island?
[Pili pants]
Okay.
Ew!
Pili, you gotta wait!
-Come on, Barfy!
-Ah, that was one time!
This is it.
This is where the coin wanted us to go.
Just like Monks wrote in his journal.
Here it is.
"Following Robinson's lead,
we cleared the way and climbed into…
the belly of a beast"?
Do you think he meant the mountain?
-Come on!
-What? Pili!
You know, why did old timey people
have to talk all poetic and crap?
Just tell me where to go!
Dude, dump out what you don't need.
We'll get it on the way out.
Roger dodger.
Okay.
This. I don't need that.
My mask.
Oh, my yoyo!
-I'll definitely need this.
-Finally something useful.
Much lighter!
You know, these kind of look like
the canvases in Papa's studio.
-Why would those be here?
-I don't know.
I thought he said
he didn't find the treasure.
[both coughing]
That smells like--
The butthole to hell.
-What do you think's inside?
-Only one way to find out.
-You ready, dude?
-Yeah.
I tracked their ATV.
They're still in the valley.
-You want me to get 'em?
-I'll kill her.
We'll get them. Mahalo, Ryan.
Anyway, are you busy on Saturday
by any chance? Or…?
No, I'm free. What's up?
Er. Would you be interested in
doing something?
I would love that, Ryan.
Talk to you later.
-Okay. Bye.
-Bye.
He seems pretty cool.
He's really cool.
Wait, are you cleaning my car right now?
It's the least I could do.
For the ride.
Okay. You're welcome
for that combination thank you and insult.
[radio music plays]
MUSIC ADVANCEMENT PROGRAM
Somebody who wants to
go to Julliard likes this music?
Can you not touch my stuff?
What instrument do you play?
Or are you a dancer?
I'm not going to Julliard, okay?
It's hard to get into Julliard
when your application's on the floor
and not in a mailbox.
What's the deal with your name, E?
Why don't you go by Ioane?
It's a good name.
It's annoying telling everybody
how to pronounce it.
The only Hawaiian name they know
is Keanu, and he's the worst.
Shut your mainlander mouth.
Keanu's a Hawaiian treasure!
You mean a sad Canadian?
Hey, the sadness just makes him hotter.
Yeah, like you know.
You're listening to Meghan Trainor.
I'm sorry.
How do you know this is Meghan Trainor?
-Because the-- The song is--
-Yeah, looks like someone's a huge fan.
-Look, let me turn the--
-What?
-[radio louder]
-[Ioane] No way!
♪ Darling tell me all the ways ♪
♪ Tell me all the ways
And you said ♪
♪All the ways ♪
♪ Tell me all the ways
And you said ♪
♪ All the ways ♪
♪All the ways
You love me ♪
-[Pili] So, this is a lava tube?
-Yeah.
[Casper] It's a natural conduit
formed by low viscosity lava flows
that created a hardened shell.
[Pili stammers] What?
-[Casper] A river of lava made this cave.
-[Pili exhales]
[Pili] That is so dope.
What happened here?
What do you think's down there?
Let's see.
Where'd it go?
[thud]
[both screaming]
[grunting and straining]
-[both moaning]
-[Pili] Ow!
Pili.
[both screaming]
[Ioane] Oh, my shoes.
These bugs.
-[Hana] Engine's still warm.
-I hope they're not too far.
Do you know why your sister
wanted to come here?
Yeah, she does this stupid thing
called geocaching.
She found a journal and Papa had a coin
and now she's sure there's treasure.
-Oh, look, it's your boy's.
-Which means we're on track.
[Ioane] Wait, wait, wait.
-What?
-Let me go first.
I'll make sure it's safe.
-'Cause you've been here before.
-It's a job for real men! Oh, sh--
-Real man. You're doing great.
-There was a step there.
Fins? Flippers?
Looks like they went in there.
-Oh, yeah, no, we cannot go in there.
-Why not?
Caves are kapu.
Sacred.
Hawaiians used to sometimes store
the remains of dead bodies in caves.
So, if that's a tomb, it's forbidden.
I just want to grab my sister
who thinks she's Indiana Jones.
If you're worried about anyone
messing up this cave, it ain't me.
Fine.
Hold on.
Just so you know,
this is not normally how we do this,
but we're desperate.
I'm sorry, but I have to enter.
I mean no disrespect
and I do this with a clean heart.
Mahalo.
Aw, is that an offering?
Yes, Ioane.
Okay.
-Me?
-Your turn.
[sighs]
[chuckles]
What's up, mountain?
Look, you looking beautiful right now.
We gotta get up in that cave, so…
We're good. We can go now.
[bats screeching]
Ladies first. [chuckles]
Look.
He must be from the Peruvian, right?
I mean, how many dead sailors
could be lying around Oahu?
Yeah.
I've never found one…
other than today, I mean.
What the--
No way!
Roly-polies.
-[Hana] Casper!
-[Ioane] Pili!
[Ioane shudders]
[Ioane] Pili?
-E?
-[Hana] Casper!
[Pili] E! We're down here!
The edge is slippery!
-What the hell, Pili?
-[Hana] Casper, you okay?
I'm okay, thanks.
You know how lucky you are
you didn't die driving Kimo's truck?
Hi, Hana. Sorry about my brother.
I know he's annoying.
Says the ass stuck in a cave
looking for some dumb urban legend.
-[Casper] It's not a legend.
-Yeah, it's real, E. Catch.
-No. There's no way.
-Bite it. You'll see teeth marks.
The treasure's real.
Between Papa's necklace
and that ring we found
on the skeleton here--
-Wait, did-- Skeleton?
-[Ioane retches]
-[Hana] As in a dead person?
-[Casper] A dead sailor.
[Hana] We need to get you out of there.
We can use my stick. Keanu.
Come on, reach!
Pili, where's my cell phone?
-Come on.
-Chill your ginormous nips. I got it.
[Ioane] I mean, they're average nips.
They're not small or big.
Give me my cell phone. I'll call 911.
What did you do to my phone?
It was an accident. I'll buy you a new one
with the ring we found.
-I'm gonna kill you!
-[Hana] Relax.
Just use mine.
[Hana] Come on, a little more.
-Come on, Casper.
-Move.
I'll do it. Take your phone.
Come here.
All right.
[Ioane] Jump,
you're just standing there.
[Hana] God. I got you.
Okay.
-Okay.
-Oh, hello.
-Shut up and lift the kids up.
-Okay.
[Ioane] Come on.
[Hana] Watch out!
No, no.
[Hana screeches]
[both screaming]
Yo, what's up? It's E. Leave me a message.
It's Mom. I…
I'm just calling to check in on you guys.
[Leilani] Have fun geocaching.
I know it's not your thing,
but it means the world to Pili
that you're doing this with her.
So, tell her that I love her.
And yes, I love you too.
Talk to you later. Bye!
[Ioane screams]
-[Casper] It was his ring in your mouth.
-[Ioane retches]
Okay, according to Monks' journal--
Not this again.
[Hana] Monks?
Like the sailor on the Peruvian?
What? It's real.
Monks and his crew
carried the treasure here.
So this is where we need to go.
This cave with the pools, waterfalls,
mountain hole,
and whatever those ropes are.
Kinda looks like a pulley system.
Let me see.
So, if we just follow what it says to do
in Monks' journal,
we'll find a way out and be okay.
No, no, no.
You don't understand.
We'll be more than okay.
We're gonna be rich!
We can pay off Papa's bills…
and stay in New York
and get Mortimer a trainer!
Hana, you could afford to go to Juilliard.
Er, how about we focus on getting out?
What's next, Pili?
We just have to go through…
the Las Fauces de la Muerte.
Yeah. Treasure, here I come.
That sounds inviting.
It means the Jaws of Death.
What are the odds it's metaphorical?
Come on, it's fine.
Really?
-What?
-It's gonna be fine!
[Pili] This is sick!
[Ioane] No, no, no.
This is really bad.
Not metaphorical.
[Casper] Stalactites are very sharp.
How will we protect ourselves?
I've got an idea.
["Pump It", Black Eyed Peas playing]
♪ Ha ha ha ♪
♪ Pump it
Ha ha ♪
♪ Wanna hate on us (who)
Be envious (who) ♪
♪ I know why they hatin' on us (why)
'Cause that's so fabulous (what) ♪
♪ I'm gonna be real on us (Come on)
Nobody got nothing on us (No) ♪
♪ Girls be all on us from London
Back down to the US S-S ♪
[kisses]
[Ioane grunts]
[retches]
[high-pitched mocking laughter]
[screams]
♪ Come on, baby, just
Pump it (Louder) ♪
♪ Pump it (Louder)
Pump it (Louder) ♪
♪ Pump it (Louder) ♪
♪ Pump it (Louder)
Pump it (Louder) ♪
♪ And say (Oh, oh, oh, oh) ♪
You're taking people fishing,
I heard that!
-I didn't! He took me last week.
-You're doing that!
That's how you know that it's good! Oh!
Okay. End of fun.
[women laughing]
-Aloha! Mahalo!
-Take it easy.
Uncle is apologizing for not bringing
the nurses avocados this week.
Oh, avocados, the big bumbucha kind?
Oh, yeah,
Uncle brings us a bag every week.
He like ohana over here.
Everybody like know how he doing.
That's right, Kimo.
Soon you'll need a bigger room
just for flowers and balloons.
All right!
Somebody checked his blood sugar?
It was high last night.
-After I take his blood pressure.
-And he took his meds?
-While you were on the phone.
-He get the kind--
Leilani.
Tina one nurse, too.
She know what for do. Let her do her job.
Kimo, try to relax.
[Kimo sighs]
So, Leilani, you live in New York now?
Yeah. She left after Kua died.
Well, visiting must make you miss home.
Yeah,
actually I was thinking of moving back.
Oh, that's good news, right, Kimo?
Now why would you do that?
To spend more time with you.
I mean, you're ohana, right?
And what would you know about ohana?
I'm gonna get some coffee.
[door shuts]
-What?
-Now why you act like you never miss her?
That's your keiki.
[Kimo sighs]
[scraping, shuffling]
[Pili grunts]
[panting]
Hold this.
What are you doing?
I just need to clarify something.
Er...
Guys, don't touch the wood.
Oh, God.
All right, let's go.
-Get your butt out of my face!
-Your face is in my butt!
Get your face out of his butt, E!
-Just move, I'll get your bag.
-All right.
And if you fart, I'm gonna kill you.
-[Hana] I'm too big for this.
-[Pili] We're almost there!
[Hana panting]
[Pili] Ugh!
[Ioane grunting]
-What's wrong?
-Your bag is caught on something.
Oh, hey, look!
[Ioane screams]
Spider scream. E, are you okay?
That sound was your brother?
Don't worry,
wolf spiders are harmless and cute.
We're lucky that it wasn't
a brown violin spider,
because, hoo boy, let me tell you--
I'll need you to kill it.
But the wolf spider is endangered!
I'm endangered!
Ioane…
don't… move.
That is not a cute wolf spider.
That… is not… a wolf spider.
Why does it have so many eyes?
Those… aren't… eyes.
[screaming] Go! Get out!
[screaming] Move!
Go!
Move!
[wood cracking]
[Ioane and Casper panting]
[crashes]
[all coughing]
Where's Casper's backpack?
-The journal's in Casper's backpack!
-Pili!
[crashing]
[heavy thud]
[all coughing]
The photo.
Pili, please tell me you remember
what the journal said about getting out.
You finished reading it, right?
Did you just ask her
if she finished reading it?
Yeah, I did, obviously.
Okay.
Then what did it say?
I remember.
So Robinson and Brown came into the cave
and they were like:
"Dude, it's raining so hard."
"Just moist and muddy and--
Yeah, and, uh, like-- Woo!"
"It stank like ammonia."
"Because of all the bat poop."
"Yeah. Mad bat poop."
I remember now. Because you fell asleep,
I took the journal,
I read the whole thing.
Robinson and Brown were talking about it:
"It's raining outside."
"It's moist and muddy." "Yeah, moist."
"Hey, yo, let's all go to Papaya King
and get a slice." "Woo!" "Yeah!"
And then they all lived
happily ever after.
They don't have pizza at Papaya King.
That's exactly my point.
You didn't finish reading the journal.
I'm a slow reader.
-"Don't worry," she said. "We'll be fine."
-I was just trying to help Papa.
No, you weren't!
You were pretending to be
a treasure hunter.
You do this all the time, and this time
you dragged us down with you.
Get over here.
What is wrong with you?
-Me? How are you not freaking out?
-I am!
I am freaking out so hard right now.
-[Hana] But you don't see it.
-You okay?
Because I don't want them to see it,
because they're 12.
Here, take this.
It's not me you need to make right by.
Your stupid head's bleeding.
Kids, come on.
[Leilani sniffles]
Hey.
Thank you.
Sorry about earlier.
It's okay.
It's just that things have been--
Stressful?
Overwhelmingly.
I know we haven't really talked since…
well, since high school.
[she chuckles]
But trust me,
Kimo's happy you're back home.
I don't think so.
Leilani…
it's been 11 years.
He doesn't want you to leave.
He's just--
He doesn't know how to show you
how much he miss you.
[she sobs]
[Casper] Wow, Pili,
you were right.
Monks left these markers everywhere.
Look, there's another one.
Good job finding those.
-Hana, look!
-Casp, hold on.
Hey.
I saw you had a picture of Mom and Dad.
Can I see it?
-I've never seen this before.
-Yeah, I found it in Mom's room.
Mom's dress is really pretty.
I know.
Do you think that was the last time
she shaved her legs?
[both laughing]
Oh, my God.
Oh, no.
-They both look so happy.
-Dad looks good.
Same crew cut as I remember.
You're lucky you remember anything.
[rainclouds breaking]
[in Hawaiian] I'm sorry.
I sorry.
I sorry for making you feel unwanted…
and a burden.
[in Hawaiian] Let's make things right.
[in Hawaiian] Yes,
let's make things right.
[she sniffs]
How can I teach your kids aloha
if I don't have my relationship
with you right first?
[speaking Hawaiian]
I want to make it right
E kala mai ia'u.
I sorry I blame you…
for my loneliness.
[speaking Hawaiian] E kala mai ia'u…
for leaving you…
and for staying away for so long.
I had to stay on the island
'cause it was my responsibility.
But I should have been there for you.
[sobbing] E kala mai ia'u
for causing you so much pain…
because I was running away
from my own pain.
[in Hawaiian] Thank you.
For coming to take care of me…
when I told you not for come.
[in Hawaiian] Thank you for your love.
Even after I hurt you so deeply.
I love you.
[in Hawaiian] I love you so much, Papa.
[Pili] What the…
[Ioane] Is the floor literally lava?
Peanuts!
[echoes]
Yo, what are you doing, Hana?
[Hana] Er... I'll be right there!
Hana's not a big fan of heights.
Then how is she gonna cross that?
You know, Hana,
we're probably not that high up.
It's not that deep. Me and Casper
will cross the bridge first.
What? No, you're not test running
this deathtrap.
-Let's not call it that.
-We're the lightest out of you two,
If anyone should test it, it should be us!
It's true. You have a lot of muscles
and muscle is heavy.
-I do have a lot of muscles now that--
-Really? Now?
-What are you guys talking about?
-Nothing. It'll be fine.
Watch.
[snapping]
[Hana screams]
[heavy thud]
There it goes.
Maybe there's some rope here.
Dirtiest pirates I've ever met.
You tidying up, Marie Kondo?
[Ioane laughs]
I love her.
-How did these guys die?
-If I had the journal, I could tell you.
I'd also know
how that Monks dude got across the pit
without building a bridge
and then built a bridge, but I don't.
Does that look like a bullet hole?
-What's wrong?
-Nothing.
[Pili] Hey, you guys! You gotta see this!
[Pili] Look! Over here!
-We found the way across!
-[Hana] How?
Just follow the ledge
and jump across here.
You ready, Keanu?
[Pili] Woo! [yelps]
-Oh, what are you--
-Tada!
-I hate it.
-It's the only way!
-You can do it!
-You got this!
Fine.
I'll just… get this over with.
[Hana] Yeah, this isn't a big deal at all.
[Ioane] This is nothing. [laughs]
Thinking about it,
the Empire State's probably
two, or three, or four,
or five, maybe six--
[Hana] Sssh!
Just stop… talking.
Okay.
Not a big deal.
The more you think about, it's really--
[shrieks]
[Hana shrieks]
-Okay. No, I can't do this.
-You can, you gotta keep--
Don't tell me what I can
and can't do. You almost fell.
Hana,
you just gotta get your mind off it all.
How?
♪ I need more details,
More text, calls, and emails ♪
♪ Be more specific, girl
I'm here to listen ♪
[Hana] What is happening?
♪ I know I'm needy but ♪
♪ Tell me you need me ♪
♪ Don't be afraid, babe ♪
♪ Come on explain ♪
♪ If you love me, love me
Love me like you say ♪
[Casper] ♪ Darling tell me all the ways ♪
♪ Tell me all the ways and he said ♪
[Ioane] ♪ If you love me, love me
Love me like you say ♪
[straining] ♪ Darling
Tell me all the ways ♪
-♪ Tell me all the ways, he said ♪
-[Hana] I hate this so much right now!
-[bats screeching]
-[Hana screams]
♪ And he said all the way!
Wooo! ♪
-[Ioane] ♪ All the way ♪
-[Ioane] Yeah!
-[Pili beat boxes]
-♪ Tell me all the ways and he said ♪
[Hana] ♪ Take me out dancing ♪
Yes!
♪ Forget romancing ♪
[both harmonizing] ♪ It's been a while
Since I've been your princess ♪
♪ Tell me your heart's blue
When I'm not with you ♪
♪ Don't be afraid, babe
Come on, explain if you ♪
♪ Love me, love me, love me like you say ♪
♪ Tell me all the ways and you said ♪
-[Casper and Ioane] ♪ All the ways ♪
-[Hana] ♪You love me ♪
[Casper] ♪ And he said ♪
[lava gurgling]
You ready?
One, two, three!
[both grunt]
[laughing] See? Piece of cake.
Are you okay?
Er. Yeah, I just have to pee.
-You look like you have to pee.
-I don't.
-What?
-What's going on?
-I don't know.
Okay, stop.
Earlier you said something
about some wack spiders--
You said we gotta go pee. I have to.
Dude, I need you to focus. Spiders.
You said something about one that's brown.
The brown violin.
The most dangerous spider in Hawaii.
-Most dangerous. Great.
-A cousin of the brown recluse.
Their venom's necrotic.
We are so lucky that we were not bitten.
Let's say one of us was bitten.
How messed up would that be?
It depends on whether or not
the bite blisters.
Like this?
Oh, that's not… great.
-Should I pop it?
-No! We have to get you to a hospital.
-What's gonna happen?
-Next would be fever and chills.
If the bite weeps pus and the skin
turns purple, it's gone necrotic.
My dad's friend got bitten
and the doctor had to scoop
the necrotized flesh from his leg.
-I need you to shut up.
-We gotta tell Pili and Hana.
We have to get out, and it'll be hard
if everybody's worried about me.
-Is that duct tape?
-Yeah.
I'm not sure that's sanitary.
Just shut up and pee.
[Pili] Woah.
Cool.
[Hana] Oh, wow!
[Casper] Jeez!
Wow!
[Pili] Why is it glowing in here?
[Casper] Dinoflagellates.
-What?
-They're like a bioluminescent algae.
But I've never heard of…
bioluminescent organisms
living in fresh water.
What's up with your hand?
I don't wanna be that guy,
but does anybody see a way out?
'Cause I don't.
These grooves look like
they go straight to the bottom.
"Straight to the bottom
and there you'll find..."
This isn't a pool. It's a tunnel!
We can't see it
because it's filled with rain water!
I'll dive in and check.
-Are you sure?
-Yeah.
Okay. [winces]
[Casper] Cold! Ah, my bits!
[Casper inhales]
Casper?
[panicked] Casper!
Hold this!
[Casper gasps]
-[Hana sighs]
-[Casper] I found it.
The tunnel is shaped like a U-bend.
Hold your breath
and get to the other side.
And I saw sunlight!
-Really?
-Yeah.
Come on, Hana!
[Hana laughs]
-You had me so worried.
-Sorry.
-You okay?
-Yeah.
Good.
They're better to each other
than we are, aren't they?
-[Casper] Guys, the tunnel's right here!
-Go ahead. We'll meet you there.
Hey.
I know you're scared, but…
I'll be right here the whole time.
Come on.
Just one second.
You can do this! You got this!
You can do it-- No, you can't.
-Monks' treasure's over there. Let's go.
-I got it. Okay.
-I got it.
-Pili, come here. I got you.
You're not acting like you got it.
Get on my back.
-I got it!
-This is for Papa.
-Okay.
-Okay, there you go.
Hold your breath. Ready? One, two, three.
[Pili muffled] Go!
-[torch thud]
-[Ioane muffled pain]
[muffled scream]
Pili! Get on my back, let's go!
[Pili gasping]
-[Hana] Pili, are you all right?
-Are you okay?
-Yeah.
-Pili, are you sure?
-[Pili] I'm good.
Okay. Well, then let's go.
Hey! Who said you can't swim?
[running water]
[Pili] Wait a minute.
I remember this cave!
The one with the mountain hole
and crown-shaped opening!
[Pili] It's the same one
Monks drew in the journal!
This is ground zero!
-[all laughing] Yeah!
-Yeah!
-[Ioane] Let's go!
-[Casper] We made it!
-[Pili laughs]
-[Casper] Watch your step.
[Ioane] Look at all these waterfalls!
[Pili] It's been here all along!
I knew it!
[Ioane] Guys, I can see outside!
[Pili] We're almost there!
[excited laughter]
[crash of water]
[Pili] Er...
Balls!
Sounds weird when I say it.
Sorry, guys,
I gotta go check on something.
-What is she doing?
-Ground zero.
The Geocache Queen
looking for her treasure.
-Hana! Reception! You're outside.
-Oh, my God.
Come on! [louder] Come on!
Go.
-E, you look terrible.
-Thank you.
Er, I'm gonna go check on Pili.
If you wanna hold Keanu for me--
Yes. Thank you.
I swear it's in here somewhere.
I just have to see it.
No reception and only 3% battery.
Are you okay?
Yeah.
I just needed a minute.
-Are you sure?
-Yeah.
You know, if Pili finds anything,
you better mail
that application into Julliard.
Why do you even care so much?
How many jobs do you work? Two?
I work at Shake Shack.
I know the smell of a fast food
employee's shirt when I fold one.
It's not just about the money.
Hawaii's a big part of me,
and I don't know if it's worth leaving
just for a shot at singing.
So you're just scared of being homesick?
I'm scared of New York making me
uncomfortable with who I am.
Remember Monks' drawing
and all those weird ropes
attached to the poles and stuff?
[Casper] Yeah, that ladder was access
to the big bag of rocks,
but where is it?
-Do you think we can climb up and find it?
-No.
-Hold this!
-Where are you going?
The pulley's buried
under 200 years of banyan roots.
[Pili] So let's pull them down.
[both gasp]
Is it weird that
I'm getting used to finding dead sailors?
Or that so many of them
died along the way,
maybe not all accidentally.
One of the guys
must have turned on the crew.
What if it was Robinson or Brown?
-What?
-Think about it.
They told Monks
the captain was gonna kill them
and take all of the gold.
[straining]
[Casper] But what if they were lying?
What if that was their plan?
So, Robinson was all:
"Thanks for carrying the gold and stuff,
'cause it was so heavy."
"Too bad you gotta… die now!"
[Robinson yells]
[swords clanking]
That would have been messed up!
[Casper] Monks and the crew
never stood a chance.
[Casper] "No one hurt badly, I hope."
"I'm gonna be moving over there."
"You guys stay here.
I'll be back to kill you."
Then, how did Monks make it
to the beach all beat up
and give the journal to my family?
Maybe he was in on it.
"I can be a villain with you.
You can train me. I can do whatever."
"Help me help you do
villainy stuff or whatever."
"Come on, what would you say?"
And they turned him.
[Pili] No way.
[Casper] And then Robinson, Brown,
and Monks took down the men.
-[muffled yelling]
-[Pili] Wait, wait, wait.
Monks would never turn on his friends.
Well, someone did.
I know these roots are hiding something.
Come on, let's pull them down.
[Pili grunting]
[both panting]
Winner, winner, treasure dinner!
Something's missing.
Hey, Casper,
weren't there three bags of rocks?
-[Casper] Counterweights!
-My bad.
Weren't there three counterweights
in the drawing?
Yeah. That one was lower,
that was higher,
and the third one was low too,
but where is it?
Oh, look, here it is.
Look! Someone must have cut it!
Yeah! If we pull it down
and get it into the right position,
it should lead to Monks' treasure.
Don't worry, Pili, I can do this.
Come on, Casper!
You can do this! You got this!
[Casper groans] Oh, man!
-Casper! What are you doing?
-I'm okay.
If we pull this down,
it'll show us the way!
We need more muscle!
I know someone who's got muscle.
Just so you know,
if you let go,
I'm not responsible for your death.
It's okay. We can still be friends.
[Pili] Hurry! We're losing light!
-You ready?
-Yeah.
One, two, three!
[Ioane groaning]
[Ioane yelling]
[Pili] Come on!
You're strong! You can do this!
-Keep pulling, Hana!
-Don't let go!
-I'm trying!
-You got this!
-Hana, pull!
-Yes!
-Keep pulling!
-[Pili] You got this! I believe!
-Let's go!
-[Ioane] It's working.
[Pili] Come on!
-[Ioane] It's working!
-Come on!
Come on, Ginger Stark!
[both groaning]
Come on, E! We need to find
a way to tie this thing off!
[rope straining]
The rope's too old! It's gonna snap!
Well, if the rope snaps,
then we won't be able to--
[thud]
-I'm okay.
-You okay?
Yeah. So are my pants.
[thud]
Widowmaker!
-[thud]
-[all scream]
If the rope comes out of the block,
the pull will be too strong for us!
Hold on! I got it!
Hurry up, Pili, faster!
-[Ioane] Go, Pils!
-[Casper] Go!
[Ioane groaning]
Hold on, guys, almost there!
I got-- [screams]
[Hana] Pili!
[Ioane] Pili!
I'm good.
Hurry, Pili!
Come on, Pili!
Come on, Keanu! Hang in there!
[Hana] Hold it!
[Pili grunting]
-[Ioane] Come on!
-[Hana] Hurry!
[Casper] Pili, hurry!
I have a confession!
I'm not as strong as I look!
I only went to one Crossfit class.
It was a free trial! I'm so sorry!
I'm so sorry!
-Shut up!
Hang in there, guys!
[Ioane groaning]
[Hana] Please hurry!
[Casper] Don't let go! Hold on, E!
I can't hold on much longer!
PILI
Guys! Something's happening!
Yeah! Ow!
Don't let go!
You guys can let go now.
-[Hana] Sure?
-[Casper] Is it safe?
Yeah, it's safe!
[Pili] Look, something's happening!
[Pili] Look! That must be the way
to Monks' treasure!
-[Ioane] We did it!
-Yeah!
[Pili laughs]
[all cheering]
-Boom! Yes!
-Yes!
-We did it!
-[Casper] We're losing daylight.
[Pili] Let's go!
[Pili] Watch your step.
[Pili] No… way.
[Pili] I told you it would be here.
I knew it! I knew it!
[Pili] I knew it the whole time!
[high-pitched] Woohoo!
[giggling]
Sick!
Cheese on rice! [laughs]
[Pili] Woo!
-[Casper] Ow!
-[Pili] Sorry.
[clinking]
[Ioane gasps]
[coins chinking]
No way.
Not bad for a stupid
fake treasure hunt, huh?
Yeah.
Hm!
-You're right.
-I know! [chuckling]
[shouting] Yeah, baby! We're rich!
[Pili screams]
-Ow!
-What? You did it to him?
We had those trade winds for a few days,
but you can say A hui hou to that,
because we won't see them for the next…
Yo, what's up? It's E.
Leave me a message.
E, I'm doing that thing where I'm going
from being worried to being mad.
Seriously, call me.
So as we go,
up until at least tomorrow
we're going to be seeing…
Kualoa Ranch?
This doesn't make sense.
Kualoa should be closed by now.
And why is E's location hours old?
Did he turn off his phone?
I'm gonna kill those kids.
-Leilani.
-I know, they're just teenagers.
-They could have texted or something.
-Leilani!
[Pili] Pili got some bling bling, yo!
I cannot believe that Robinson, Brown,
and Monks' torches still work.
-How are your matches not wet?
-Got a waterproof case.
Nice.
Dope or trash?
[laughs]
-Keep it. Keep all of it.
-[Ioane laughs]
-Ow!
-I got you.
I think it's stuck.
Okay. All right. Okay, and…
This belongs to me now, right?
No. Mine.
You know what we should do?
What?
Selfie!
Okay. Ready?
-On three. One, two--
-[camera shutter sound]
[she chuckles]
Didn't that go under with you?
How is it still working?
Waterproof case, mainlander.
Get with it.
Guys, come here.
Ready?
-On three. One, two, three.
-[camera shutter sound]
[all laughing]
[Hana] Oh, my God. You got a good smile!
What's that?
That's…
weird.
[muffled whispered voice]
[Hana gasps]
God, I knew it! This cave is kapu!
-[Casper yelps]
-[Pili] Eugh!
What does that mean?
It's sacred. I was worried this cave
would be a tomb and it is.
I still don't see the problem.
We used to believe
that when a person died,
their bones held all their mana,
their power.
To protect the mana,
bones were hidden after death
so that their location
would stay secret forever.
-So that's someone important?
-Yes.
I don't know who, but it doesn't matter.
We're disturbing their tomb,
and we shouldn't be here.
Okay. Let's just grab what you can.
-We'll figure a way out.
-No!
We can't take any of this with us.
[Ioane] You can't expect us
to leave all this.
How are we gonna sell or show this
without telling where you found it?
-What does it matter if we do?
-I said the remains need to stay hidden.
You also said: "We used to believe
the bones held power."
-Now you don't. So who cares?
-You should.
You're native Hawaiian. Kanaka.
We tell anyone about this place,
they'll want to know who that is.
This cave will be crawling
with thrill-seeking tourists
who wanna feel like Indiana Jones.
People like me.
Pili, that's not what I meant.
You're right though.
Monks, Robinson, and Brown
must have found this place by accident,
not realizing it was a tomb.
Papa kept telling me
there wasn't any treasure.
Just the stories in the book.
He's a liar!
Because he knew.
He found this place.
It's why he hid that entrance
and cut that rope.
He kept this place a secret
out of respect…
and aloha.
So, I will too.
Are you serious?
[Ioane] You're the reason we're here!
[Casper] But they're right.
It's the right thing to do.
[Ioane] Oh, great. Now you too.
Come on. One second.
What the--
[Casper exhales]
You know what? Y'all do y'all.
I'm gonna do what I gotta do
to get back home to New York.
You're literally tomb raiding.
This isn't even
whoever that is's treasure.
But it's their tomb.
Anything and everything left in it
is like an offering to them.
They're dead.
And dead people own nothing.
I didn't know she was gonna go up there
to get the treasure all by herself.
You're trying to tell me
that my kids are at Kualoa Ranch,
possibly inside a mountain,
looking for some fabled Spanish gold?
It's not a fable.
When I found the treasure,
I understand why Monks
want leave it alone.
He never went back,
because the dude's kapu.
You should never disturb a place
that does not want to be disturbed.
Then the Night Marchers went after Monks!
No!
See? Taking treasure,
no powerful bones coming at me.
[wind howls]
What was that?
[gust of wind]
What the heck?
[wind howling]
[Casper] Weird.
[crashing and shuddering]
Run!
Come on! Hurry!
[Pili] Hurry!
[Pili] Watch your step!
[Ioane] Go!
Wait! Keanu!
-[Ioane screaming]
-[Casper] Come on!
-[Pili] Night Marchers?
-No, Pili, it's just a stupid story!
-[Hana] Are you talking about lapu?
-[Casper] Go!
-We gotta get out of here!
-How?
The banyan roots!
Guys! I have to do one last thing.
I'll be right back!
[Ioane] Pili, what are you doing?
Come back!
Listen, cave,
I ain't got no beef with you,
but I've gotta do this… for my papa.
Sorry, Keanu.
Yes!
[water roars]
Gotta go!
[crashing]
Guys, we have to go! Like, now!
[all retching]
What's that smell?
They're coming.
Guys, whatever you do,
do not look at the lapu, okay?
If you do, you're dead.
-Bobby Shytles!
-That turd was right!
E, take this.
-Hana, are you ready?
-What is this for?
Just remember, the banyan roots
are stronger than they look
and so are you.
Do you trust me?
-Yes.
-Then jump.
[Hana squealing]
It worked!
Okay, let go!
[Hana squealing]
[both laughing]
-[loud blaring]
-[both screaming]
We gotta go!
On the count of three! One, two,
three!
[Ioane screaming]
[Pili screaming]
[muffled] E!
[shouting] E!
E, where are you? E! [shrieks]
Move your arms and legs.
The shore is right there!
Go! Just go!
[Pili coughing]
[gasping and coughing]
Hana!
Casper!
Guys!
Where are you?
E!
[Hana and Casper gasping]
E, are you okay?
[Hana and Casper panting]
Come on, over here!
Over here! Over here, over here!
[Hana panting]
[Casper] Is he okay?
Oh, God, he's not breathing.
Move, I know CPR.
One. Two. Three. Four.
-Come on.
-Five. Six. Seven. Eight.
Nine. Ten.
Come on, E! One. Two.
Three--
[Ioane gasping]
[coughing]
You had me so scared, you butthead!
[Ioane] Hey,
good idea with the bunion root-- banyan--
[Casper] Uh oh.
[Pili gasps] Holy cow!
It's a brown violin spider bite.
-[Hana] What?
-I am so sorry for breaking our bro code.
It's nothing. Go on.
-[loud blaring]
-[all wincing]
What's that sound?
We gotta go!
-[Casper] Come on, guys!
-[Hana] Get up!
[Casper] Get him up! Hurry up!
-Uncle, time to moi moi. Get some rest.
-Yeah.
[wind howling]
[Leilani shouting] Pili!
Ioane!
[Casper] That was creepy.
It's all right. Come on, let's go.
-[Pili] Come on, E. We're almost out.
-[Ioane groaning]
[sings in Hawaiian]
[singing continues]
-[Pili] Why are they still after us?
-[Hana] I don't know!
-[Leilani] Pili!
-[Kimo singing]
-[Leilani] Pili! Where are you?
-Mom?
-[Ioane] Mom!
-[singing continues]
Mom!
-Mom!
-[Leilani] Oh, my God!
[distant drumming]
Are you okay?
Oh, my God!
-[wind roars]
-[singing continues]
[conches blaring]
-[all groaning]
-[Kimo singing]
[singing continues]
[Kimo] Protect my children.
[Kimo] Protect my ohana.
[drumming gets louder]
-[wind roaring]
-[Kimo resumes singing]
[Leilani] A shed! Go!
[Hana] Come on!
[Pili gasping]
[Kimo's voice fades]
[Ioane] Over there!
-Put your eyes down!
-[Leilani] Put your head down!
Don't look up until they leave.
Pili! Come on, Pili!
Protect my children.
Protect my ohana.
Don't look up until they go away.
[Leilani] Oh, my God.
What happened to your hand?
[Hana] It's okay.
It's okay, Casper.
[Hana] It's okay. I'm here.
What are you doing?
It's okay. Hold on.
How did you get that?
I'm sorry, Mom. I'm so sorry.
I just didn't want to lose Papa.
It's okay, baby.
It's okay.
[Leilani] It's okay.
[whispered indistinct voices]
-[crash]
-[indistinct gruff voices]
[all yelping]
[whispered voice]
[male voice] Mine.
Kua.
[Pili] Dad.
I promise, Dad.
[Leilani sobbing]
[conches blowing]
[Pili panting]
WAHIAWA GENERAL HOSPITAL
[Leilani] And remember,
we can't talk about this with anyone.
No Night Marchers, no treasure, nothing.
It's all huna.
So, wait.
E told me your face melts off
if you look at a nightmarcher.
Why didn't that happen to us?
Because you get the koko of your father,
the koko of a fallen warrior.
The lapu saw you as ohana.
So, Dad?
He protected all of us?
Mhm.
So, where the boy?
[Hana chuckling]
Ow! Watch the hand!
Or you could be better
about keeping it out of the way, E.
Actually, it's Ioane.
-Really?
-It's a good name.
Ioane is a very good name.
Especially when you say it.
[door opening]
[door shuts]
-[Pili] Sorry about losing your journal.
-Ah, it's okay.
Probably better off anyway, huh?
-[Pili] Can I ask you something?
-Yeah.
What really happened at the end
for Robinson, Brown, and Monks?
Before they hid the treasure,
Monks thought
how lucky he was to survive,
but it had nothing to do with luck
and everything to do about greed.
Robinson and Brown turned on their crew.
They was never gonna split the treasure.
I knew Monks wasn't a bad guy!
[Pili] Maybe Robinson knew
Brown was gonna double cross him!
And they started fighting!
They lost their weapons,
and they looked for stuff to fight with
because the cave was so messy!
And there were coins all over the place!
They fought with the candlesticks.
There are pieces of them everywhere!
"Oh, dip!"
Their fight got so crazy,
they had no idea they ran into a tomb.
[Kimo] Yes, they make pilikia,
trouble in those caves.
[Kimo] And after they disturbed the tomb,
all of their bad intentions
came back upon them
and then they heard the sounds of drums.
-[distant drumming]
-[wind howling]
The lapu had been awakened!
The last thing Monks heard
before he went jump
was Robinson and Brown's screams.
[inaudible screams]
So, Monks was never a bad guy?
Nah, he was never one bad guy.
He was just a kid…
trying to get back to his ohana.
So, after he jumped,
is that when our ohana
found him on the beach?
[Kimo] Ae.
And now you know the whole story, yeah?
Thanks, Papa.
-[Kau roaring]
-[Leilani laughing]
[Leilani] Watch out, Ioane!
Here comes Daddy!
Can you take care of Mommy
and your sister?
[Leilani] Pili, girl! Look at Mommy! Pili!
-[Ioane] Look at her face!
-Yes, there we go! [chuckles]
-[Kau] Stand up!
-[Leilani] Baby Godzilla!
[Leilani] I'm gonna miss you.
-I love you.
-I love you, too.
[Leilani] No! I got the camera!
[Leilani laughing]
-[Ioane] Dad was so handsome.
-[Pili] I know.
[Ioane] That's where I got it from.
-[Ioane] Oh, you don't want to see that.
-[Pili] Hey, stop!
-[Ioane] Watch it! Pili!
-Okay, my mo'opunas.
[kiss]
-[Ioane] Mahalo, Papa.
-Mahalo nui!
[Leilani] Okay,
it's time for a family meeting.
So…
I've made some of, well…
all of the most impactful decisions
of our lives.
I don't want to do that anymore.
Because we're ohana.
So here's the situation.
We can't afford to settle
all of Papa's bills…
unless we sell our apartment.
In Brooklyn.
Which means…
either Papa will have to move to Brooklyn…
or we'll have to move to Hawaii.
So, let's talk about it.
BROOKLYN, NY
O'AHU, HI
♪ We're going to the beach today ♪
[Pili] ♪ We're gonna laugh ♪
♪ And sing our cares away ♪
[Ioane] ♪The sun is shining on our face ♪
[both] ♪ And we can take it in
And let it out and say… ♪
[Kimo] What we gonna say, family?
Ohana, here we go!
[all] ♪ La-la-la-la-la-la-la ♪
[harmonizing] ♪ La-la-la-la-la-la-la ♪
♪ La-la-la-la-la-la-la ♪
-[Kimo] Shoot!
-[Leilani laughs]
[singing in Hawaiian]
[all] ♪ For you and I ♪
[all laughing]
[continue singing in Hawaiian]
[all] ♪ For you and I ♪
[continue singing in Hawaiian]
-[Kimo] Very good brah.
-♪ For you and I ♪
[continue singing in Hawaiian]
♪ For you and I ♪
[laughing]
[continue singing in Hawaiian]
♪ For you and I ♪
[slower] ♪ For you and I ♪
[cheering]
[women singing in Hawaiian]
[singing continues]